Guide to the Roy A. Long Collection ARS.0086
Archive of Recorded Sound
Roy A. Long Collection
1952-1980
ARS.0086
Long, Roy A.
6 boxes: 132 open reel tapes
Archive of Recorded Sound
Open reel tape recordings from approximately 1952 through 1980, including various performances from Stanford University, as well as pipe organ music, live jazz and big band music, the Monterey Jazz Festival, the Carmel Bach Festival, and a steel drum band in Antigua, all recorded by donor Roy Long.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Scope and Contents
The Roy A. Long Collection consists of open reel tape recordings from approximately 1952 through 1980, featuring performances from the Stanford University Music Department, as well as pipe organ music, live jazz, and a variety of other music, all recorded by donor Roy Long, of Palo Alto, California. Long was a graduate of Stanford and an engineer at the Stanford Research Institute. Among the Stanford material are recitals and church services (featuring Sandor Salgo, Herbert Nanney, Putney Aldrich, the Stanford Symphony Orchestra, and the University Chorus), the Men's Glee Club, and Tresidder Memorial Concerts. There are recordings of pipe organ at Stanford, Grace Cathedral, and Holy Trinity Church in Menlo Park, as well as organs in San Jose, Fresno, Los Angeles and elsewhere. In his travels, Long recorded the Hell's Gate Steel Band in Antigua, West Indies in 1956, and a band in Niuafo'ou, Tonga. Other local performances Long captured include the 1965 Carmel Bach Festival and the 1958 Monterey Jazz Festival, and several by the Peninsula Symphony Orchestra. Jazz musicians in the collection include Woody Herman, Dave Brubeck, Harry James, Stan Kenton, and Louis Armstrong. Although many of these tapes are undated, at least some appear to be unique live performances recorded locally by Long, such as Woody Herman at the Tin Pan Alley in Redwood City, California. An additional donation of transfers on optical disc overlaps with these tapes, and this is noted when known. Programs and recording notes are inserted into some tape boxes. Despite that fact, the majority of tapes are minimally annotated, and may only be identified for certain after audition.
Source
The Roy A. Long Collection was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by Roy A. Long in December 2008.
Indexing Terms
Aldrich, Putnam; Carmel Bach Festival.; Hell's Gate Steel Drum Orchestra.; Monterey Jazz Festival.; Nanney, Herbert, 1918-1996; Salgo, Sandor; Stanford Symphony Orchestra.; Stanford University. Dept. of Music.; Jazz; Live sound recordings; Organ music; Steel drum music
- 1. Organ Music
  - Denis A. Des Rosiers, St. Nicholas Church Dedication, Los Altos. [program enclosed], 1980-09-14; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - Elkus, Hunter Meade Residence Organ Pasadena, 1957-11-30; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Maurice John Forshaw, Trinity, 1953-12; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 3)
  - Maurice John Forshaw, Memorial Church, Stanford University (reels 1, 2, 4 and 6), 4 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 3)
  - Maurice John Forshaw Jean Langlais recital no.1, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 3)
  - Maurice John Forshaw and Bob Keine (organist and choirmaster) at Holy Trinity Church, Menlo Park [notes and obituary enclosed], 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 3)
  - Maurice John Forshaw at Concordia [notes enclosed], 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
  - Tom Hazeltine - The Paramount Oakland Organ, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - Holy Trinity Church, Menlo Park 1 and 2 [notes enclosed], 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 3)
  - Bob Keine at Holy Trinity Church, Menlo Park, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 3)
  - Jean Langlais at Grace Cathedral, 1954-02-26; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 4)
  - Max Miller at Holy Trinity Church, Menlo Park, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - Michelle Morran, Palo Alto Chamber Orchestra. Presbyterian Church of Menlo Park [program enclosed], 1974-12-27; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Herbert Nanney, St. Marks Dedication, 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 3)
  - Herbert Nanney, Stanford Organ, 1953-07; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
    Compact Disc available
    These recordings may also be available on "Herbert Nanney at the Murray Harris organ at Stanford," Archive of Recorded Sound ACD 33.
  - odds and ends, theater organ, Reel No. 154, 1 7" open reel tapes (Audio 1)
  - Flor Peters, Immanuel Lutheran Church, San Jose [program enclosed], 1965-10-29; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
  - Richard Purvis at Grace Cathedral, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 3)
  - Richard Purvis, Peninsula Symphony Orchestra at Grace Cathedral, San Francisco [program enclosed], 1965-01-17; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - Tom Rhoads at Fresno Congregational Church, 1968-04-01; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - Tom Rhoads and Robert Magin, Long Beach First Congregational Church, 1957-11-29; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    68 rank new Moller organ demonstration and misc. selections
  - Tom Rhoads at St. Marks, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Tom Rhoads at Fresno Congregational, 1968-04-01; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Tom Rhoads #1 o/o Bob Briody, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - Skinner Organ demo, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - St. Mark's Church Christmas program [notes enclosed], 1965-11-07; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - Tiny at the Fox Theater, Oakland 1-3, 3 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 3)
  - Warner Theater, Fresno, 1968-04-01; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
- 2. Stanford University
  - Sandor Salgo, William Crosten. Sonata Recital., 1952-01-15; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
  - Sandor Salgo, William Crosten. Sonata Recital. Memorial Auditorium [program enclosed], 1953-04-14; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
  - Sandor Salgo, Stanford Symphony Orchestra. Memorial Auditorium. Handel, Blacher, Strauss., 1955-12-04; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 6)
    These recordings also available as Archive of Recorded Sound ACD 23.
  - Tresidder Memorial Concert 1 and 2, 1956-04-08; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
  - Sandor Salgo, Stanford Chamber Ensembles, Herbert Nanney. Concert of Baroque Music - Concert and Rehearsal reels 2, 4 and 5 [programs enclosed], 1956-11-18; 3 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 6)
    These recordings also available on Archive of Recorded Sound ACD 27.
  - Stanford Church Service, Memorial Chapel [program enclosed], 1956-11-18; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 6)
  - Sandor Salgo, Stanford Symphony Orchestra, Stanford University Chorus, Memorial Auditorium [program enclosed]. Handel, Barber, Strauss., 1956-12-02; 3 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
    These recordings also available, with track identifications, on Archive Recorded Sound ACD 21.
  - Sandor Salgo, Stanford Symphony Orchestra, Memorial Auditorium [program enclosed]. Pergolesi [since reattributed], Harris, Berlioz., 1957-02-19; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
    These recordings also available, with track identifications, on Archive Recorded Sound ACD 22.
  - Stanford Symphony Orchestra, Stanford University Chorus, Putnam Aldrich, harpsichord. Poulenc, Gabriel, Ratner, Wagner. 1 and 2 [program enclosed], 1957-11-17; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 6)
    These recordings also available as WAV files on Archive of Recorded Sound ACDI 2.
  - Stanford Symphony Orchestra Rehearsal - Poulenc, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
  - Stanford Men's Glee Club, Spring Club Reel No. I and II [program enclosed], 1958-04-13; 2 7" open reel tapes (Audio 1)
  - Stanford Symphony Orchestra Strings, Putnam Aldrich, haprsichord. Harpsichord Concerto, 1 10.5" open reel tape: pancake (Audio 6)
  - Sandor Salgo, Joy, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
- 3. Carmel Bach Festival 1965
  These recordings at least partially available as WAV files on Archive of Recorded Sound ACDI 3.
  - '65 Bach Festival, 1965; 1 7" open reel tapes (Audio 1)
  - Orfeo pt.1, 1965; 1 10.5" open reel tape: pancake (Audio 5)
  - Magnificat, 1965-07-23; 1 10.5" open reel tape folders (Audio 5)
  - Mozart. Piano Concerto K 903, 1965-07-22; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 3)
  - Vivaldi. Concerto E Flat Major, Aldrovandini. Sonata for 2 Trumpets, 1965; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
  - St. Matthews Passion 1-3, 1965; 3 10.5" open reel tapes: pancake (Audio 5)
  - Bach. Cantata 1, Coffee Cantata, "squeaky", 1965; 1 10.5" open reel tape: pancake (Audio 5)
- 4. Steel Drum Music
  - Steel Drum Music Tape 1 Ben Fogle, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Hell's Gate Steel Drum Band, Tradewinds Hotel, Antigua [musical manuscript enclosed], 1959; 3 7" open reel tapes (Audio 1)
    These recordings are available on Archive of Recorded Sound ACD 28.
    Hell's Gate Steel Drum Orchestra.
- 5. Jazz
  - Louis Armstrong mono, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - DB 1 and 2 [i.e. Dave Brubeck?], 1954-05-28; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 5)
  - Dave Brubeck, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Woody Herman And Thundering Herd at Tin Pan Alley, Redwood City # 3 [newspaper clippings enclosed], 1964-03-04; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 2)
    These recordings also available, with track identifications, on Archive Recorded Sound ACD 20.
    Scope and Contents
    The newsclipping is a Ralph Gleason article about Herman playing in San Francisco and Redwood City. When producing a CD-R transfer of this tape, Long wrote these notes: "In March 1964, Woody Herman and his Herd performed for four nights at the Tin Pan Alley in Redwood City. The sessions were broadcast 'live' from KJAZ in Oakland. In fact, I made tapes and they were driven to Oakland after each set for broadcast... We had 8 mics, 5 Telefunkens, my Altecs, and for the bass a good old 44BX ribbon that I insisted on finding... Of the dozens of tapes that we made I have only one. No one knows what happened to the rest."
  - Harry James, Memorial Hall, 1956; 2 10.5" open reel tapes: pancake (Audio 6)
  - Stan Kenton and his Orchestra, Stanford Memorial Hall, 1956-11-18; 3 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 4)
    These recordings also available, with track identifications, on Archive Recorded Sound ACD 29.
  - Monterey Jazz Festival, 1958-10-04; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
    1. Gerry Mulligan Quartet; Modern Jazz Quartet 2. Louis Armstrong, etc.
  - Peterson Piano [Oscar?], 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
- 6. Miscellaneous
  - Chicago Symphonic Band, Showcase for Symphonic Band, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Covenent 4 For Horn and Orch. [notes enclosed], 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Donizetti. Maria Stuarda. Sutherland, San Francisco Opera House [newspaper clipping enclosed], 1971-11-16; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 2, Audio 4)
  - Evensong At Holy Trinity Church, Menlo Park [program enclosed], 1958-10-12; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
  - Handel. Alcina. Bonynge, London Symphony Orchestra, Sutherland KXKX, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 5)
  - Haydn. Trumpet Concerto, Italian Concerto. Sworosky, Vienna Philharmonic Symphony Orchestra, Adolf Holler, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Larry 1 and 2, 2 10.5" open reel tapes: pancake (Audio 2)
  - Larry at Lost Weekend, 1957-01-14; 2 7" open reel tapes (Audio 1)
  - Larry at Lost Weekend, 1957-12-29; 2 10.5" open reel tapes: pancake (Audio 2)
  - Tom Lehrer, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Leo Jazz and Harp Solos, 1 10.5" open reel tape: pancake (Audio 2)
  - Max Wedding, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - University of Michigan Band, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - Montagu Three, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Niuafo'ou, Tonga 1, 3, 2 7" open reel tapes (Audio 1)
  - Peninsula Symphony Orchestra, Erick Friedman soloist. San Mateo High School Auditorium [program enclosed], 1963-11-08; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Frank Owen Harpsichord, 1957-12-30; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Stereo Demo, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - Strauss, Ein Heldenleben. Antheil, Ballet Mecanique, 1955-10-03; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4)
  - Sutherland- Excerpts, Handel, Collection, 3 7" open reel tapes (Audio 1)
  - Trumpets and Trombones Jul.23, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - unidentified, 1 5" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Wedding, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)